Guide to the Herbert Gans Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series II: Subject Files, 1944-2004
  - Transaction Magazine, 1968-1973 (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - Urban sociology, 2000-2001 (Box 47, Folder 10)
  - White House Conference “To Fulfill These Rights,” 1965 (Box 47, Folder 11)
  - Worksharing--Correspondence, 1982-1986 (1 of 2 Folders) (Box 47, Folder 12)
  - Worksharing--Correspondence, 1982-1986 (1 of 2 Folders) (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Worksharing--Talks and Papers, 1980s (Box 48, Folder 2)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1949-2004
  This series contains correspondence arranged both chronologically and by correspondent. The general correspondence is arranged chronologically; correspondents include Gans's fellow scholars and students, admirers and critics of his work, editors and publishers, and journalists and public figures with whom he did not maintain a regular correspondence. Very little personal information appears in these letters and memoranda. Much of this correspondence is of a routine or formal nature.
  Correspondents arranged alphabetically include David Riesman, economist John Kenneth Galbraith, and Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist Max Frankel, all of whom corresponded regularly with Gans over a long time period. Others, including a number of American sociologists — among them Daniel Bell, Todd Gitlin, Nathan Glazer, Seymour Martin Lipset, Robert Merton, Daniel Patrick Moynihan, William J. Wilson, and Francis Fox Piven — wrote and received letters to and from Gans intermittently over several decades. Similarly, Gans corresponded in spurts, especially in the 1990s, with a number of journalists and critics, among them Russell Baker, Gail Collins, Maureen Dowd, Paul Goldberger, Nicholas Lemann, and Jim Sleeper; as a group they offer a glimpse into Gans's passionate engagement both with the news and with the manner of its reporting.
  The series also contains correspondence touching on Gans's time at Columbia, the bulk of it pertaining to administrative and personnel issues within the Sociology Department. Correspondence related to particular subjects remains interspersed throughout the writing and subject files. For instance, in addition to the correspondence between Gans and Riesman in Series III, Riesman correspondence on the subject of The Levittowners can be found in Subseries I.1.
  - General, 1950-2004 (9 of 80 Folders) (Box 48, Folder 3 to 9)
  - General, 1950-2004 (10 of 80 Folders) (Box 49, Folder 1 to 10)
  - General, 1950-2004 (10 of 80 Folders) (Box 50, Folder 1 to 10)
  - General, 1950-2004 (9 of 80 Folders) (Box 51, Folder 1 to 9)
  - General, 1950-2004 (7 of 80 Folders) (Box 52, Folder 1 to 7)
  - General, 1950-2004 (9 of 80 Folders) (Box 53, Folder 1 to 9)
  - General, 1950-2004 (8 of 80 Folders) (Box 54, Folder 1 to 8)
  - General, 1950-2004 (7 of 80 Folders) (Box 55, Folder 1 to 7)
  - General, 1950-2004 (8 of 80 Folders) (Box 56, Folder 1 to 8)
  - General, 1950-2004 (5 of 80 Folders) (Box 57, Folder 1 to 5)
  - Abbott, Andrew, 1995-2001 (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - Baker, Russell, 1969-99 (Box 57, Folder 7)
  - Becker, Howard, 1998-99 (Box 57, Folder 8)
  - Bell, Daniel, 1972-2000 (Box 57, Folder 9)
  - Collins, Gail, 2000-2004 (Box 57, Folder 10)
  - Columbia University
    - Coming to Columbia, 1968-71 (Box 57, Folder 11)
    - Sociology Department, 1971-2002 (1 of 5 Folders) (Box 57, Folder 12)
    - Sociology Department, 1971-2002 (4 of 5 Folders) (Box 58, Folder 1 to 4)
    - deBary, Theodore, 1973-1976 (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - McGill, William, 1971-1977 (Box 58, Folder 6)
  - Dennis, Everette, 1984-2001 (Box 58, Folder 7)
  - Dowd, Maureen, 1993-2001 (Box 58, Folder 8)
  - Ellsberg, Daniel, 1967-1970 (Box 58, Folder 9)
  - Frank, Barney, 1987-2003 (Box 58, Folder 10)
  - Frankel, Max, 1977-2000 (Box 58, Folder 11)
  - Friedman, Milton, 1974-1975 (Box 58, Folder 12)
  - Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1979-2004 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Gitlin, Todd, 1969-1994 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - Glazer, Nathan, 1951-1998 (Box 59, Folder 3)
  - Goldberger, Paul, 1977-2001 (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - Goodman, Paul, 1960-1961 (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - Harris, Fred, 1967-1985 (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - Hartke, Vance, 1970 (Box 59, Folder 7)
  - Hirsch, Paul, 1976-1984 (Box 59, Folder 8)
  - Hughes, Harold, 1971 (Box 59, Folder 9)
  - Humphrey, Hubert, 1968 (Box 59, Folder 10)
  - Jacoby, Tamar, 2002-2004 (Box 59, Folder 11)
  - Jordan, June, 1969-1972 (Box 59, Folder 12)
  - Lemann, Nicholas, 1994-2002 (Box 59, Folder 13)
  - Lewis, Oscar, 1966 (Box 59, Folder 14)
  - Lindsay, John, 1965, 1968 (Box 59, Folder 15)
  - Lipset, Seymour Martin, 1961-1994 (Box 59, Folder 16)
  - Lynch, Kevin, 1950s (Box 59, Folder 17)
  - Marris, Peter, 1962-1999 (Box 59, Folder 18)
  - Merton, Robert, 1953-2001 and undated (Box 59, Folder 19)
  - Meyerson, Martin, 1959-1969 (Box 59, Folder 20)
  - Mondale, Walter, 1968 (Box 59, Folder 21)
  - Moynihan, Daniel Patrick, 1966-1997 (Box 59, Folder 22)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1955-1970 (Box 59, Folder 23)
  - Musil, Jiri, 1989-2002 (Box 59, Folder 24)
  - New York City Officials, 1979-1995 (Box 59, Folder 25)
  - O’Connor, Alice, 1993-2001 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Offe, Klaus, undated (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - Piven, Francis Fox and Richard Cloward, 1966-2001 (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Podhoretz, Norman and Midge Decter, 1961-1968 (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - Purnick, Joyce, 1995-2001 (Box 60, Folder 5)
  - Rainwater, Lee, 1966-1968 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  - Riesman, David, 1949-2002, (7 Folders) (Box 60, Folder 7 to 13)
  - Rustin, Bayard, 1966-1985 (Box 60, Folder 14)
  - Schlesinger, Arthur Jr., 1961 (Box 60, Folder 15)
  - Schorr, Alvin, 1978-2004 (Box 60, Folder 16)
  - Seeley, John, 1955-1962 (Box 60, Folder 17)
  - Sleeper, Jim, 1984-1992 (Box 60, Folder 18)
  - Uchitelle, Lou, 1996-2002 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Wacquant, Loic, 1992-2001 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Wanner, Eric, 1991-2004 (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - Weaver, Robert, 1962 (Box 61, Folder 4)
  - Wilson, William Julius, 1987-2001 (Box 61, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Teaching Materials, 1957-2000
  This series contains lecture notes, syllabi, reading lists, and examination questionnaires Gans produced during some four decades as a teacher of urban planning, sociology, public policy, and mass communications at the University of Pennsylvania, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Columbia University.
  - University of Pennsylvania
    - Planning 544: The Development and Structure of the Contemporary Community, 1957 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Planning 900: The Sociology of the Urban Community, 1959-1960 (Box 61, Folder 7)
    - Sociology 24: Mass Communications in American Society, 1959 (Box 61, Folder 8)
    - Sociology 11: Urban Sociology, 1958 (Box 61, Folder 9)
    - Assorted Planning and Sociology Courses, late 1950s (Box 61, Folder 10)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology
    - 11.51: Urban Sociology and Social Policy, 1969-1971 (Box 61, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence re. academic appointment, 1969-1970 (Box 61, Folder 12)
  - Columbia University
    - 4047 Urban Sociology and Social Policy--Syllabi, 1971-1979 (Box 61, Folder 13)
    - 4047 Urban Sociology and Social Policy--Syllabi, 1990-1995 (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - 4047 Urban Sociology and Social Policy--Exams, 1979-1995 (Box 62, Folder 2)
    - 4047 Urban Sociology and Social Policy--Lecture Notes, 1972-1975, (2 Folders) (Box 62, Folder 3 to 4)
    - 4047 Urban Sociology and Social Policy--Lecture Notes, 1986-1995, (2 Folders) (Box 62, Folder 5 to 6)
    - 4052 Equality in America, 1972-1975 (Box 62, Folder 7)
    - 4099 Field Methods, 1976-1986 (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - 3940 Social Policy and Social Planning, 1979 (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - 3415 Sociology of News and Journalism, 1981-1983, (3 Folders) (Box 63, Folder 3 to 5)
    - 9240 Mass Media and Popular Culture Research, 1995-1999 (Box 63, Folder 6)
    - PhD Examinations in Urban Sociology, circa 1976-2000 (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - Mass Media in an Urban Society, circa 1967 (Box 63, Folder 8)
  - Urban Sociology--Assorted Materials, 1960s-1990s (Box 63, Folder 9)
- Series V: Mixed Media, Undated
  This small series includes a few photographs of sociologists who taught at Columbia between the late 19th and the 20th century, and four discs of undated Edison Voicewriter Dictaphone recordings. It is unclear what Gans recorded on these discs.
  - Columbia Sociologists--Early 20th Century, Undated (6 photographs) (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Columbia Sociologists, Undated (17 photographs) (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Edison Voicewriter Dictaphone Recordings, Undated (4 discs) (Box 65, Folder 3)